So um what like to do today is chat with
you about the full cycle of a deep
learning project. And as I promised in
the first lecture rather than me talking
at you for an hour in 20 minutes or
whatever um would love for this to be
much more interactive. And so what I'm
going to do is illustrate this an
example, but also ask you a bunch of
questions along the way about what you
would do if you are the one working on a
project that I'm going to use as an
illustrative example. Okay? So plan for
this to be quite interactive and please
interrupt anytime and ask questions
since I think that's why uh you know we
I want to do this in person here at
Stanford. Um so one of the reasons why
developing machine learning or deep
learning or other types of AI projects
including AI projects using large
language models or agent AI workflows or
whatever is that AI projects are
different than traditional software
engineering projects. So one of the
biggest difference between AI projects
of the many different flavors supervised
learning OM based um you know generative
AI based is that in traditional software
projects you write code and you control
your code right whatever code you want
compile it your code does what you tell
it to but AI projects
you know
involve both code as well as data that
you train your algorithm on and you
almost never know what strange and
wonderful things there are in your data.
For example, if you're working on a face
recognition application, that's a
running example I'm going to use today.
Then as you're just getting started on
the project, you actually it's really
difficult to know in advance um what you
find in the data. Is the lighting of the
faces good? Do you struggle with people
with very long hair or people with short
hair? Um, do people making weird facial
expressions make your system struggle?
Do people wearing glasses make your
system struggle? So, data is so rich
that a lot of time you can't predict in
advance what your AI system is going to
do. Not because you don't control the
code. You can write whatever neuronet
network or whatever code you want, but
you don't know what's in the data. And
this is why unlike traditional software
engineering, um machine learning
development is a much more iterative
process where you just have to build
something, see how it works and then
through a process discover almost
discover what is in the data and
therefore what you should be doing to
change your code to make your overall
system perform. And this is also true
not just for this is true not just for
deep learning based systems. This is
also true for modern large language
models. If there's been a lot of hype
buzz about how OM's large language
models are hard to control. I think
there's a lot of excessive hype about
that. You know, kind of fear monging.
There's a little bit of that. But one of
the reasons why none of us know in
advance what OM do is because was
trained on a lot of data, more data than
any human could possibly look at. And we
just don't know, you know, with
precision what is in all that data that
the ARM was trained on. And so because
we don't know the data, we can't really
look at all the massive tens of
trillions of tokens of data was trained
on. It's hard to know exactly how a
large language model will perform. Which
is why building agent applications or
building large language models based
applications is also very empirical or
very experimental. Meaning you just have
to build something then see where it
goes well, see where it goes poorly and
then use that to fix problems and that's
how you drive progress. That make sense?
So because you control your code, but
you don't really know, it's hard to
control the data. And this is true both
of the data you have stored in your hard
disk. You kind of have, I don't know,
terabytes of data stored in my hard
disk. I don't really know what's in my
hard disk. Um, and the thing you really
don't control is what data the world
will give you in the future. So we
deploy a system in the world, uh, say
face recognition, which I we should talk
about. Will people wear a thick heavy
scarf that covers parts of their face
when it's winter? You just don't know.
there all these things in data that will
surprise you and and if you don't even
control your past data that's already in
hotness, you certainly can't control
your future data.
So, um it turns out that a lot of
machine learning classes talk about
building models,
right? And you learn a lot from the um
online videos uh about how to build
powerful deep learning models. But it
turns out that building an overall
machine learning system or a deep
learning system
has a lot more work than just training
models. But um if you look a lot of
causes there's actually a very strong
focus on modeling because I think that's
what academia has focus on right we can
train models evaluate models publish
papers on models and so you find that a
lot of causes focus on you know training
a good deep learning model and that is
absolutely important. Um but because we
know how to evaluate models, different
research groups can benchmark different
models. There's a lot of academic
research work on that that's reflecting
a lot of causes. But this is just a
small part of what you need to do if you
want to build an effective deep learning
system. And what I want to do today is
um go outside this small box of models
to give you a broader view of what it
feels like to develop a deep learning or
AI or machine learning system. Okay. And
this is what it often uh so this is what
um building a deep learning system
would be like which is first
you know
right
specify the problem figure out what
we're actually working on the running
example I want to use today will be to
build a face recognition system or face
rec system for um security for deciding
when to unlock a door and then Kan
talked about some face recognition which
abate face rec architectures last week
as well but um specific application I'm
going to talk about this is something
I've worked on some built actually I
built one of the commercial systems that
um uh uh that uh for for this is um if
this is a door um and you know this is
well you or a friend or or maybe a
someone that you don't want to let in
approaching. If we have low camera,
sorry, bad drawing, take a picture of
whoever's approaching the door and
decide whether or not to unlock the
door, right? So, face recognition to
decide who's authorized to enter like a
restricted location like a your
corporate office building or your house
or whatever. Um, and actually one one
common use case that um one of my teams
built was a key cipe key cards. So,
sometimes key cards get stolen. Um and
so one of the systems we deployed you
know fairly large office complexes was
uh um if you swipe a key card we also
just take a picture then soon discard it
to make sure that the key card is held
by the person you know whose face is
shown on the key card. So it makes it
harder if someone to steal a key card to
gain unauthorized access to to like the
office complex. Right? So so so I'm
going to use this as a the motivating
example for today. And after um
specifying a problem
typical process is then right
um sometimes the open source models you
can download but let's say for today
that the open source models aren't good
enough you want to train your own model
but simple process we get data
you know
design a model,
right? Train a model. Um, and then we
will iterate
through these steps a bunch of times
until the model looks like it's
performing well enough. Um, and then
after that, we have to deploy it.
Um
and uh monet maintain the model. Okay.
So I'm actually going to talk a bunch
about uh multiple of these steps today
because I want you to come away with a
feel for when you're working on a real
machine learning application
what it what what the important steps
you will face are right um and so as I
alluded machine learning development is
very iterative process so for these
three steps
we often drive a um rapid development
loop
where we
you know
I'm sorry
design the model
train it
analyze the results and then maybe
design or update the model or the data
or something and iterate around this
loop many times for you um are
satisfied.
And um all right, just one more detail.
Um it turns out that for face
recognition, the very common
architecture which you learn in detail
about uh later in the online videos is a
neuronet network called a Siamese
network. And what that does is a
neuronet network that takes as input two
pictures
and two pictures get fed to a neuronet
network or a deep learning algorithm
and it's the job of the deep learning
algorithm to tell us are these two
pictures the same person or different
persons right because um if you're
trying to set this system say for your
house and maybe you have I don't know a
few family members or roommates you want
to let in then it's I don't It'd be
quite annoying if you had to retrain a
neuronet network for every single home.
So the most common way to do face
recognition is of a neuronet network
that inputs two pictures and the job of
the neuronet network is tell me are
these two pictures at the same person
and then the way you set up the system
is to input a few registration pictures.
So take a picture of yourself, take a
picture of your roommate, take a picture
of you know any family members you want
to have access. So then when someone
comes, you can quickly check if the
person that just showed up is one of the
people that's authorized and then let
them in. And then the corporate key card
swipe example, if someone swipes a card
and you know my card says this is
Andrew's card, then I'll quickly pull up
my registration picture to double check
if I am if I seem to be the same person
as the you know Andrew that was
registered. Right? So this is how um
this is a typical neuronet network
architecture.
All right. So, I have a question for
you. One thing one one thing I'd like to
do today is um walk you through a number
of scenarios and invite you to think
about what decision you would make if
you're the CTO of a startup uh building
these technologies. Right? So, so my
question for you is um if you're the CTO
of a startup building the next face
recognition system um and if your
lawyers have said you aren't allowed to
download data from the internet right so
let's not download data from the
internet for this application how would
you go about getting data to train the
system so what you need is a bunch of
pictures of people
right to train a neuronet network to say
you know are they the same person or
not. So maybe take take a few minutes to
think about it and then I'll see if you
can raise hands and give some answers.
And one one specific question I have as
well is um how long would you take to
collect data before you start training a
model, right? So I think um uh well you
need to get data. We've designed a model
I guess and then you need to train
model. So what does the timeline look
for you? We specify the problem, you
know, we'll design the model. How many
hours or days or weeks would you spend
to get data and how before you start
running, you know, gradient descent,
right? Maybe I see a hand out.
>> Oh, sure. Go ahead.
>> Are we doing like everyone around the
world or we like
Bay Area, America
or like this?
Let me let me leave it a little bit more
open-ended. Say you just graduated from
Sanford and you're CTO of a three person
startup um building this thing uh that
eventually hopefully you sell all around
the world but your goal is to just get
started with with the three of you
working out of you know Palo Alto
California
right and and do it as your real self
right with the resources that you have.
All right. Anyone want to venture an
answer? So, how would you how would you
get data to train the neuronet network?
>> Go for it.
How about using
service?
>> Yeah, cool. Video streaming service. By
the streaming service, you thinking
like, you know, Netflix and Hulu, or are
you thinking like um security videos?
>> Oh, like Zoom. I see. Cool.
>> I see. Cool. Cool. Great. Cool. All
right. Service. How How long do you
think it'll take to to do that? uh
couple.
>> Yeah. Cool. All right. Cool. Thank you.
Right. Creative idea. Any idea ideas how
would you go about and get data? Yes. Go
ahead. This one I work for a threeperson
startup but had a larger company. I
would put a camera to have the camera
and ask the employees if they would
like.
>> Yeah. Cool. Awesome. Right. Stick a
camera there. I'll let let people, you
know, opt in, right, to to get the
picture taken. Cool. I think I saw a
hand up. Go for it.
>> Oh, sorry.
I see. Cool. Right. Yeah. By your own
people, you like grab some friends and
also they'll, you know, give you that
LinkedIn photo, give you some pictures
with your camera, girl. Yeah. Cool. I
like that. That's fast. I like that.
Any other ideas?
Oh, go ahead.
That's interesting. Yeah. Stanford to
send an email. Cool. But I love
Stanford. Stanford is a wonderful
institution. Also, that's going to take
a while.
Really creative idea. I like I like the
creative ideas.
So let me share with you one guiding
principle for how I would encourage you
to approach this problem of data
collection. I appreciate all the
creative ideas actually. Um one of the
frameworks I often use to decide how I
collect data is speed. um because I find
that um as especially you're building a
startup right uh one of the in my
opinion one of the strongest predictors
for whether a startup will succeed and
also whether a small innovative project
in a large corporation you can be a
giant corporation but if a team of three
you know work on a small innovative
project in a big big company I find that
one of the biggest predictors for the
chance of success is just the she speed
of execution the sheer speed getting
stuff done. And so when I'm um saving a
team and brainstorming different
tactics, I will gravitate toward the
tactics that let me get a data set very
quickly. And quickly usually means, you
know, like one or two days. Um even if
it ends up with a inferior, smaller,
lower quality data sets or whatever. Um
because I don't really know what
problems I'll see in my data. And the
quicker I can, you know, get a data set,
train a model, see where it goes wrong,
the quicker I can then discover what's
wrong with my data and fix it. Um, true
story, chatting of a CEO that told me he
once actually once um he he actually had
spent um uh I think it was over $und00
million, definitely more than tens of
million dollars. Spent a lot of money
buying a company for his data. Um, and
then he actually said, "Hey, Andrew, I
spent all this money to get all this
data, you know, can you help me figure
out how to monetize this, how to make
money off of this?" Right? And I kind of
look at him and go, "Boy, I kind of wish
I hadn't done that." Right? Um, and what
I find is that um the value of data, it
it's just so difficult to know in
advance, right, what's important and
what's not important about data. So, for
a lot of these tactics, um, uh, for
example, I think student ID is an
interesting one. Uh, but you know, are
student ID photos weird in some way,
right? Or are they too expressionist or
or people smiling too much in student
IDs? I actually have no idea. Um,
actually my my Stanford ID, I look
really weird in my Stanford ID. Um,
uh, or um uh and and I think you and and
or or or uh and actually like the idea
of sticking a camera and just letting
people, you know, come up and and opt in
and take a picture if you can do it
quickly. Um and I think in a big company
or even in a small startup if you know
it's important to respect user privacy
right individual privacy but if you can
stick a camera in some place you know
that doesn't um kind of a what's the
word um invade people's privacy that
don't want to be any part of this but
let people opt in take the pictures of
permission if you can do that in days I
find that to be valuable one of the
thing I found for quite a few of my
projects found that you know Stanford
students Our community here is pretty
cosmopolitan with people from all around
the world. We're not fully
representative of the world's, you know,
distribution of people, but we actually
do have people from all around the
world. A lot of Stanford people actually
very nice. So, one thing I've done
multiple times is when I need to collect
data, uh, we'll go to places on campus
with high foot traffic. Turns out
cafeterias have very high foot traffic.
And we just ask people, hey, work on the
project. Can I get a sample of your
voice? Can I take a picture of you? kind
of with you know really informed
constraint tell people is it okay if I
do this I've been delighted at how
collaborative right Stanford students
are uh uh um but and and I find that one
thing I've often done is gone to my
teams and said um we have two days to
collect data is like whatever it's 11:52
a.m. now let's figure out what we're
going to do by uh what day is it Tuesday
let's figure by Thursday 11:52 a.m. So
let's give us 48 hours and let's
brainstorm how can we collect data and
it's fine that the data is isn't all
there find that the data is low quality
but that velocity lets us more quickly
create a model figure out what's wrong
with the data and then or retweak
how we collect data right so I find that
some teams they'll ask um how can we
collect the data we need and how long
and then ask how long would that take
that usually leads to much slower
execution. I instead tend to go to my
teams and say we're two days or one day
or maybe a week right some short time
span like that and say what's the most
creative you know respectful responsible
but creative way you can use to collect
data in a short time span and one of the
ways to think about that too is training
a model takes I don't know let's say it
takes two days maybe take more like one
day right if you can train a model in a
couple days then I would not spend you
know like whatever, right? Two months to
find data to train a model because then
this becomes a huge bottleneck because
you can train a model relatively
quickly. Let's take a commensurate
amount of time to design a model or or
design the data as to train a model and
depending on how long it takes to train
a model sometimes train a model you know
needs to run overnight. Um I actually
see teams sometimes take one day
iteration loops around this the
fastmoving teams I work with we often go
around this loop once per day uh for the
smaller models and we're training a
large air foundation model sometimes
training a model takes weeks or even
months then the process can be different
if if your if your model run is going to
be you know two months then yeah maybe
it makes sense to spend you know a
couple months to get the data really
right but for face recognition you could
train that overnight or actually in a
couple hours quite easily easily. So, it
makes sense not to spend massive amounts
of time before you go to train the
model. Does that make sense? And because
um oh the word empirical means
experimental, right? Sorry, I've used
the word a few times today. And um I
think uh uh we we we say that machine
learning is very empirical process,
meaning it's very experimental process.
You have to do it, see what happens, and
decide what to do next. I know that
sometimes others have criticized our
field as like we never know what we're
doing. We just try stuff and see what
works and and you know there's a little
bit of truth to that. Um uh I think
understanding neonet networks
hyperparameters architecture that is
really valuable. So we don't just try
stuff at random but because we don't
know what's in the data we do try a lot
of things and then drive a the sprint
process understand what works and what
doesn't and then use that to navigate
forward. Does that make sense?
And then I just say there's one
exception to the advice I'm giving here,
which is if you're working on a project
that you have worked on many times
before. So, you know, whatever. I've
built a bunch of face recognition
systems. So, I kind of have a sense from
previous experience and from reading
research papers that certain things I
know are just not going to work if I
have, you know, a 100 images, right? So
there's some face recognition systems I
know I probably need at least 50,000
images before it'll have any hope of
working. So because of that prior
experience having gone through that loop
a lot I now have a basis to say okay I
do need 50,000 images then I might
invest up front and put more effort up
front to to get those 50,000 images. But
I think for most applications you work
on for the first time if you don't have
a academic literature to justify certain
larger data investments or if you don't
have the prior experience yourself then
um I would focus on the speed of
iterating around this loop. Make sense
um
all right and to relate this to uh large
language models based applications as
well. A lot of us, a lot of you are
probably well, you may be building
applications by prompting OM and calling
an API, right? Like a like a OpenAI or
Anthropic or Gemini or Metal Lama or
whatever API to get things back from.
One of the reasons that too is a very
experimental a very iterative and
critical process is because when you
write an OM prompt, you don't really
know in advance how well it's going to
do because it was trained on data that
none of us have really looked at. And
that too is why instead of um theorizing
for a long time about what prompt to use
an inm you know just try it out and then
it's by doing that you then see the
problems and um then your focus can be
on fixing the problems. sense and in
fact there's a lot of discussion on
responsible AI how do you make sure AI
systems are safe or they don't have kind
of unforeseen circumstances and because
a lot of the theorizing you know you can
only theorize so much I find that if you
want to build safe responsible AI
systems one of the best ways to do that
is to just build it and then experiment
with it in a sandbox environment just
don't let it all in the world until
you've tested rigorously
But just go build something and then you
know test it, probe it in the safety of
your own laptop, right? Don't let it and
innocent users and and have some weird
impact on on innocent third parties. But
it's only by building and then probing
it that you can figure out where can it
go wrong, where will say inappropriate
things, where would it, you know,
respond inappropriately to certain user
queries and then that tells you where
the problems are that you work on
addressing. Okay. All right. Yeah.
Question.
>> How do you use
[Music]
Oh, sorry. Sorry again.
>> How do you use that to figure out what's
wrong?
>> Yeah. Right. Um, great question. So when
you analyze something is wrong with your
model, how do you use that to take the
next step forward, right? Um that's a
big topic that we'll talk at length
multiple times in some of the videos and
also in some future uh uh lessons. But
maybe long story short, um one of the
things you could do is change your
neuronet network architecture. You may
realize that maybe the signing network
isn't working or read the literature
architecture. The other thing you can
often do is change your data. Um, so
dataentric AI is a discipline of
systematically engineing your data to
build a successful AI system. And it
turns out that you build a face
recognition system. Let's say I I like
your hat stamp hat. That's cool. But you
may let's say hypothetically that you
find that the system has really
struggles recognizing people that are
wearing hats. Then you may say, "All
right, I need to get more data with
people wearing hats, right?" And and so
it's often that um looking at what goes
wrong which we call error analysis that
then gives you the insight to say oh it
works well on these types of data or
these types of users but the struggles
of these type of users in data so can I
fix my data or get more data just on the
subset of cases it struggles with and
that's a very common um motion that's a
very common process for then driving the
performance of your system and and this
is also why um blindly going out to grab
more data willy looney. That's often not
a good strategy because it's just too
much data to get. Do I want more, you
know, data with people with, you know,
long hair or short hair or people with
facial hair? Sorry, too much hair. Um,
too many hair examples or, you know, do
I want people with um, uh, wearing a
scarf covering part of the face or
people that wear glosses where they
don't wear glosses or people that, you
know, are slightly turned away. There
there's just so many different types of
data you could invest effort to get more
of that until you build a system, see
where it goes well, see where it goes
poorly, is really difficult to decide
where to get more data and just get more
data of everything under the sun, that's
very slow and expensive. And I think um
part of the hype about the value of data
has led people to have a sometimes
overly simplistic view of data, right?
you know, yes, of course, I want more
data, but just grabbing more data of all
types of data is a very inefficient,
very expensive way to improve my system.
And even if you look at the way that
frontier models are trained right now,
it's not a game of just grabbing more
data of anything under the sun. It is
identifying the subcategories whereas
valuables invest to get high quality
data. Which is why if you look at um it
turns out in AI where there there are
two clear buckets of value in LM right
there's the general answering people's
questions I think you know open I try is
doing really well there Gemini anthropic
have momentum but there's a general
questions and then one of the verticals
is really valuable is AI for coding
assistance so I think you know claude
has been ahead for a while but open AI
you know I don't know Gemini 2.5 pro
some of the models are making really
good progress in coding as well. And if
you look at the team, look at the work
that the frontier teams are doing to
improve coding. Building irerrerative
agentic workflows is part of it, but
also finding clever ways to come up with
coding related data is also part of it.
And if you want your LM to do better on
coding, you don't grab data willy-nilly
with low quality random internet chat,
social media, whatever data, right? but
instead having high quality coding
related data is how you can have a
focused effort to improve your own
ability to to to code. A lot of these
things are actually um uh yeah I I I
feel like um the the like more data is
better that is absolutely true but it's
also overly simplistic data is not
monolithic there subcategories of data
and having a view on what piece of data
to really invest in getting a lot more
of that's really important to um being
efficient in how you improve your system
performance. That make sense? All right.
Well, we'll talk more about error
analysis in this later. Um, any other
questions?
Cool.
All right. Yeah, go for it.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. So as you collect
data um the quality of data matters a
lot too. Um which is why and and and I
think um data quality is uh is tricky I
think. Um when building an application
for the first time I would still focus
on speed and collecting some data
quickly. But as you then analyze where
your system is going well, where it's
doing poorly, you often find that um the
quality of data really matters. Um, so
try this time. I should talk about this
now later.
Um,
I'll come back. So, so let's see what's
good. All right, let me let me talk
about LM1. Um, there's a lot of
lowquality random chat on the internet
that's not that useful for training LMS.
But I think you know this is actually
now well known that if you if you can
legally access very high quality written
authored articles of books they're
highly edited very insightful that's
very high quality data for training
arms. Um and I I'll give an example
later as well for face recognition. It
turns out that um you know blurry images
right would be a a lower quality than
sharp in focus images assuming that's
representative of how you want to
recognize people's faces. So that that
really matters as well.
All right. Anything else?
Cool.
>> All right. Oh yeah, go for it. um
question about the data how close they
need to be to the task we want them to
do. For example, in space recognition
number two picture
trying to model just object
[Music]
it's much faster but we're moving away
from the ideal task we want to do. So
what is the balance here?
>> Yeah. So right just repeat for Mike. Um
how important is it that the data you
collect is similar to the distribution
of things you want to work on. Um I
think it's important but not as
important as most people might think. Uh
so it turns out that um uh it turns out
one of the reasons uh neuronet networks
have been so effective is because when
you build a very large neuronet network
you can throw all sorts of data into it
including data that is you know not uh
perfectly tuned to your test set
distribution and it often doesn't hurt
so long as the network is big enough.
So, so you rais the example, what if we
have it identify two identical objects,
right? If it's generic objects like I
don't know, water bottles and markers,
maybe that's too far a field. But, um,
if we were to use, let's say, you know,
simulated cartoonish characters, right,
that look really different than real
humans, my guess is it probably won't
hurt at all and may even help a little
bit. And so throwing in a lot of data,
if you train a large neural network with
a lot of capacity to absorb even some
slightly relevant data, um it usually
doesn't hurt and might even help a
little bit. But how much it helps is
another empirical question that'll be
problem dependent and we often just have
to try it out. But um I think maybe you
know like uh in the past people used to
have an obsession that the data you
train on has to come from exactly the
same distribution as the distribution
you test on. that used to be how machine
learning was done I don't know like 10
15 years ago that's really not true
today anymore I think we're very
comfortable and I think when when
neuronet networks were much smaller
where we could train very small models
there was a sense that you didn't want
to distract the neuronet network with
irrelevant data right because computer
was expensive with few parameters and
you distracted on irrelevant stuff maybe
it gets less good at the cas you really
care about but if you can train it
bigger the real network which is getting
easier and easier these days. Um then
it's become much more okay to toss in
some data that that hopefully isn't
incorrect data. I think incorrect data
is a problem but just irrelevant
examples hurts much less because big
neural networks is like a human brain
right? you know, I don't know. The fact
that whatever the fact that I learned to
play the piano, you know, probably
doesn't make me worse at AI, right?
Because because hopefully my brain is
big enough to learn to play the piano
and learn some stuff about AI. Um uh and
I think as neuronet networks get big
enough, they can learn some other
irrelevant things and also do well the
core task you really care about. But
this was less true when you know if if
my brain was really small then uh um I I
don't know any are fans of Sherlock
Holmes but I think Sherlock Holmes had
an attic theory that your brain has only
so much capacity so you got to forget
some stuff to learn new stuff but when
train very large neural networks that's
that's much less true
cool
all right thank you for all the
questions um so what I want to do is
just keep going through this flow right
so we talked about your data design
model, train a model. We'll talk a lot
more about error analysis later this
quarter of how to figure out where your
algorithm is still subpar and where to
um focus efforts to improve it. But what
I want to do is um give you a sense of a
deployment. Right? So
all right.
So when you have trained a model is
often um a bunch of software engineering
work to then maybe take your model host
in the cloud or local server and have it
run inference. Right? So a very common
architecture for deploying machine
learning model will be that you have a
new network as a piece of software. um
you deploy it maybe on the cloud hosted
service so that your software can accept
a picture or accept two pictures and
reply back you know do I unlock the door
or not is this the same person or not so
that's kind of bunch of software engine
work that needs to be done but in
practical deployment settings um I'll
actually tell you it turns out that if
you're building a practical face
recognition system you probably find
that if you are trying to um unlock a
door you know to a corporate campus is
too expensive or too slow to stream
video 24/7 to cloud to classify every
frame at 30 frames per second to see if
you know there's a person that you
should unlock the door for. So in
practical face recognition systems um
what we end up doing actually right so
so actually let's take the example of uh
um someone walking up to the door to
your home to your door at home um uh and
you want to see if there's someone there
they should unlock the door for right so
a lot of systems will actually have
image from the camera and then uh try to
build a system um all right
right so what we have so are
right is a system that takes as input an
image and maybe a reference image. Uh
neuro network says do I unlock the door
or not? But it turns out that if
streaming video is too expensive,
classifying every frame is too
expensive, we'll often end up with a
system like this.
Um,
I'm going to
well with VA sensor visual activity
detection.
And what this does is a usually low
cost, low power, inexpensive compute job
to run to just very quickly maybe try to
figure out is there a human face there?
Um because it turns out actually if
you're building something unlock your
front door, you know, to you and your
friends. If you look out my front door
in my house, like it's pretty boring.
You know, there's there's a there's a
there's a wall. We see over the street,
but nothing moves most of the time. So
it's very obviously almost all of the
time it's very obvious that there's no
one outside my front door trying to be
let in and be very wasteful to stream
all that video to the internet for
classification. Right? So visual
activity detection is usually a low cost
low path system to just very quickly
decide should I do the work
of um sending this to the larger face
recognition system neon network that may
be hosted on the cloud to have it do the
much more computationally expensive work
to decide you know zero or one do I
unlock the door or not. Okay, so this
type of um optimization
in order to make the system
computationally feasible to deploy is
fairly common and um I'm going to give
you two options for how to implement VAD
and I'm going to ask you to reflect on
them and then tell me which one you
would pick to get started. Okay. So
option one
is a non-machine learning based method
which is um
see if the number of pixels changed
is greater than some threshold epsilon.
Right? So uh if the camera is stationary
maybe looking at a wall most of the time
the pixels barely change because you
know it's just a wall. Um and so you can
write a little bit of code using you
know some image library like pill python
imaging library or some simple write a
few lines of code to just say has the
number of pixels whose RGB values that
change more than some threshold has more
than you know 10% of the pixels change
compared to what it looked like a second
ago um in order to see if there's
anything in front of your camera to even
decide to pass this to a more high part
neuronet network Right.
Option two
would be to train a small neural
network.
Right. So, uh, face recognition is a
pretty complex task. You have to look at
multiple cues on the face, look at the
eyes, look at the mouth, look, you know.
So, that tastes a relatively large
neural network. But just taking a quick
glance to see is there even a human in
front of my door. That's a much simpler
task. So option two would be training a
very small very low power very
lightweight neuronet network um to just
very quickly tell you do you think
there's a human there um and then use
this train model to decide is it worth
passing on to a much more powerful
neuronet network running in the cloud
with a lot more resources to make the
final determination. Okay. So if you are
the again CTO or the person started
building this, how would you what would
you how would you start? We'll give
everyone a few second reflection on
this. Now get people get people's
thoughts.
>> All right.
I think it's very much dependent. You
might live in a street where people walk
by every time
change might
um so it depends on what type of problem
you have. We can also build an option
that you can make it
simpler.
[Music]
>> Yeah. Right. Cool.
>> Yeah. Right. Cool. All right. Just just
repeating my mic. So problem dependent
depends on whether you're on the street
with a lot of people walking past. Maybe
consider other algorithms. You know,
they're even cheaper than small unit.
Cool.
just model. This is not
for that. We can probably just use
option
while we collect more data and then
replace that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Cool. Great. So, use option
one in the short term uh and then maybe
replace that with option two or more
data. Yeah. Cool. Was very very
options like because
is very simple. Um, only
>> Oh. Oh, sorry. So, use Oh, use both
options. So, put both in the pipeline.
Oh, that's interesting. I see.
>> All right. So, see if option one let
option one see if anything change. If
something's changed, then pass the
smaller network. Okay, that that's cool.
That could work.
Yeah. Cool. Yeah, that could work. So,
it could cascade multiple steps. Yeah.
>> How much would it cost us to actually
run the neural network
if it's cheap to run
because then you don't have to worry
about someone coming to the door?
If it's more expensive, then I would
option.
>> That's cool.
make sure we're not wasting a bunch of
money.
>> Cool. Yeah. Right. Yeah. So, how
expensive is it to run this new network
in the cloud? So, um actually, so I
would usually want to design both of
these to run at the edge, meaning on the
device. Um
>> Oh, this one.
>> Uh
so, it turns out that is streaming video
is fairly expensive. Um so I think um uh
uh
yeah I I I feel like boy I don't have
numbers at tip of fingertips but I think
um running this 247 is not feasible. So
we definitely need something to filter
it down. Uh but sending you know I don't
know few images every minute is probably
not a problem.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
Oh, sorry.
>> All right. Sample certain time. Sample
certain frames of the video in order to
get all of them. Yes, I guess so. Yes.
Although um Yeah. Although I I think if
you have a video of my front door
um you need a way to sample other than
random I guess right because uh lots of
time nothing happens uh unless you take
one frame per minute I guess which would
be okay but then we don't want someone
waiting there for a full minute before
we finally get around to sampling it and
then sending it. So yeah, go ahead.
>> Or could that be?
>> Yeah. Could we use the same images for
training this network to train this the
option two network? Uh maybe. I I I
think it's actually one of those things
I would I would say we have to try it
before we know if it works. Might be
doable. depends a lot on what data we
collected to train the bra neural
network. Yeah. Um, cool. Anything else?
All right, let's take take a couple. Go
ahead.
How about use option one? Keep a really
low threshold so we send very few
regions. Is that what you mean?
>> Yeah, I think uh would that be
reasonable to try? Um well, right. So
long as we don't miss too many people,
but yeah. Right. Right. Let's take one
last comment. I'll share share
perspective on how
>> Yeah. Right. Yes. Yes. So, one of the
weaknesses of option one is if there's a
tree swaying in the background or if you
see a road and there's a car that drives
by or if it's a busy street, the car's
driving by all the time or the
neighbor's cat comes and visits, those
will trigger this, right? So, those are
downsides.
So, let me show you a perspective of how
I would approach this and and what what
we actually do. Um, so if you're the CTO
of a startup implementing this, to me it
again comes down to um speed. Right. And
so what I would ask is how long does it
take to implement option one and how
long does it take to implement option
two? And I think everyone made good
points about the pros and cons of these
two options. And if you're actually
doing this, the approach I would take
is, you know, just ask what can I do
really quickly so I can then deploy it
and see whether it works and I'll fix it
if it doesn't work. Because I think
these insights like will trees swing in
the background affect it? You know, it
turns out it turns out it actually does
probably, but maybe not if the wind
isn't that strong or if um right but but
it's very difficult to know answers to
questions like these because you don't
really know until you stick on a bunch
of cameras in front of doors and see the
data. Then you can get more confident in
how well option one works. like I don't
know how often does the neighbor's cat
actually come by and uh if there's a car
that drives paws are the cars usually so
far away that it doesn't matter because
the number of pixels but the car is
small right so all of these are very
empirical questions is really difficult
to answer and the fastest way to get
answers is just implement something
quick and dirty and then run it see what
goes wrong and then fix it so what
happens on and tell you for what what
the experience of a lot of face
recognition teams is um because option
one is so quick to implement. This is
like I don't know five lines of Python
or something, right? Um and and get get
an hour to write it for you. Just get an
hour to write the five lines of Python
for you. Uh so you can implement this in
you know 20 minutes maybe even less.
Whereas this I think will take you at
least many hours maybe longer to
implement. So my instinct would be to
start to this and it turns out having
built me face recognition systems I'll
tell you this actually doesn't work well
enough for all the problems people raise
and so we wind up going to this but
implementing this also gives you
insights into where it's going wrong and
I'll give you one example of um uh one
insight that you know we and many other
face recognition teams have which is it
turns out that um uh when you're
approaching ing a camera that's trying
to recognize your face, there are some
frames that are going to be really clear
and in focus and a lot of frames are
really blurry, right? If you just look
at video of someone walking toward the
camera, sometimes just, you know, when
I'm stepping, sometimes the velocity of
my face is higher and sometimes it's
lower, right? That's just what it is.
And so sometimes my face is in focus,
sometimes it's more blurry. And it turns
out that if you can select out the high
resolution frames and feed that to face
recognition, you get much higher quality
results. Right? So this is the kind of
stuff that I assume, you know, most
people would not know about until you
work on a system like this. But it turns
out that when I was working on a system
like that, having a system to not just
do VAD, but also
capture the video and then deliberately
select not just one but maybe five
frames that are high resolution and in
focus of the person that actually gave a
significant boost to the accuracy of a
face recognition system. And I mentioned
this as an example of the sort of
discovery that you'll have only when you
implement one of these systems. Maybe
even implement this system. But you
implement the system, you see, boy,
we're trying to recognize a lot of
pictures from blurry very faces. Maybe
we need to do something about that.
Right? And this is um driving that
empirical process that may then lead you
to train a neuronet network both to see
if there's a face but also to see if the
picture of the face is in focus to
select out that frame for downstream
processing. Does that make sense? And
this is why um you find that for some
meaningful fraction of questions I asked
in in in in class, the the the thing
that the speed has to do is often the
right answer because that that obsession
with speed really lets you go in and
figure out what's in your data and
improve your system more efficiently.
Right. Um
so
Right.
So so yeah. So what happens in practice
starts with this discover how it doesn't
work because it doesn't actually work
and tell you that and then figure out
but use those learnings to do this.
Yeah.
Yeah. So is there a is there a sense of
what is a good classification accuracy
approx is actually really difficult. Um
one of the common benchmarks you learn
more about this in um the third module
on the online videos as well is uh uh
building machine learning systems is
easier if we have a reference level of
performance uh like a aspirational
target accuracy which is often human
level performance. Um so and and so uh
it turns out that um the way you
diagnose bias and variance which talk
about later in this course is easier if
you know what's an achievable level of
accuracy and very often we'll use what a
human expert could do as achievable
level of accuracy. Um and then uh in the
case of face recognition definitely
under controlled environments were
better than humans. So, uh, definitely
actually the AI systems we build,
they're way better than I am at
recognizing human faces. And I think AI
systems are better than I would say
probably the vast majority of humans,
maybe all humans at this point at really
distinguishing of two pictures of the
scene. And then and then then it gets
really difficult. Then actually gets
more difficult once you're even better
than humans. Um uh but those are uh yeah
but but at least but until you're as
good as humans on a on a certain task
using a human level performance is often
a good benchmark. And then if you're
doing something that even humans can't
do well um like it turns out you're
recommending online books or movies or
whatever humans aren't actually that
good at that. I think most of us have a
hard time recommending good movies even
to our closest friends. AI actually
probably does it even better than many
of us do as humans. then it th those
things is harder to establish a
baseline.
Cool.
All right. Now, one
final aspect
I want to touch on is um after deploying
a model to monitor and to maintain the
model. Um,
one thing that often happens is you
train a machine learning model, works
great. You know, does one your training
set, does one in your test set, works
great and then you deploy it and then
annoyingly the world changes and your
system no longer works, right? So we
sometimes call this um data drift or
concept drift where the distribution of
data the world gives you is different
than what you had in your training set
or concept drift which is with the input
output mapping your X to Y changes in
the world compared to your training set
but to to to ground this um if you're
training a face recognition system now
in you know I don't know when it's not
too cold here in California you get
faces of a certain distribution But as
we approach winter, if it starts to rain
more, people wearing scarves, rain
jackers, you know, people look
different, right? Or or maybe um maybe
we approach next summer, more people are
wearing sunglasses,
then the data distribution changes. um
or if you train a system based on data
here in California but we then decide to
deploy it you know in a different
country where people's uh dress
differently or where their appearance is
different the world keeps on giving us
different data um and so
one of the jobs of I think us as machine
learning engineers is to put in place
systems that monitor this type of
concept drift or data drift and fix
problems as they arise. is when you're
out building machine learning systems, I
have seen a segment of AI engineers that
think their job is to do well on a test
set, right? And so I've been in a bunch
of these conversations where um the
machine learning person will say, "Look,
I did well on the test set. My job is
done." But then a product owner or
business owner will say, "No, your
system doesn't work. Look at all the
ways it does not work." And then if the
machine learning person says, "Well,
that's not my problem. I do on the test
set. I think that's not a constructive
way to move it forward. So I encourage
you to think of yourselves if you're
building machine learning system. I
think of my job as building something
that works. And that can be different
than building something that works on a
test set. So if ever you're working on a
product and someone says, you know, I
know you did well on the test set, but
your system doesn't work. I would
encourage you not to respond, but my job
is to do well on the test set. I
encourage you to think about why doing
well on the test set doesn't translate
to doing well on the application that
people actually care about and then
they'll lean in and go and fix that.
Right? And one of the common problems
for why doing well on a test set doesn't
translate to doing well in real life is
if the data distribution changes in
which case you may need to update the
distribution of data you're training on
um in order to capture what it has
changed in the world. And um just a few
other examples I I I feel like you know
the world gives us new data all the
time. So if you're building a web search
engine um sometimes uh sometime
sometimes a new politician is elected or
there's a new movement or some new video
goes viral or I don't know Taylor Swift
releases a new album. I don't know
whatever and then people are suddenly
searching for a brand. I thought someone
I thought I get a lot from that. No art.
No way. nails no swift easier. All
right.
Um uh uh but then suddenly a lot of
people are searching for a brand new
thing. Um and so the distribution of
data you get is different because the
world has changed. Um or um I've done a
lot of work in factories. There's
actually a reasonable chance that cell
phone you have in your pocket may have
been inspected by software that right my
teams wrote. Um but you know sometimes
the materials change or uh there's a new
machine installed in the manufacturing
line and this machine makes a new type
of scratch on the cell phone. So data
changes in inspection lines as well or
one one thing that actually surprised me
when working on self-driving cars. Um,
one of the things I was working with, we
trained a lot on data in California. And
then when we took the cars to Texas, um,
you and I as people, we can drive just
fine in, you know, California or in
Texas. But it turns out the traffic
lights look really different in Texas in
California, right? So traffic lights,
horizontal, vertical. I think part of it
is that they're very high winds in some
parts of Texas. So a lot of traffic
lights tend to be strung up differently
to be robust to high winds, right? And
so traffic lights actually look pretty
different in Texas. So the models we
train in California, they don't work in
Texas. We got to get new data, refresh
the data. So a lot of that is a process
of um monitoring and maintaining the
model even when something in the world
changes.
And um before going on to monitoring the
model performance and maintaining it,
one interesting
difference in performance between this
and this is
option one is a very simple model,
right? It it basically has one parameter
which is epsilon, the fraction of pixels
that change. And so this because it's so
simple is actually very robust to
changes in distribution. For example,
say it's a hot summer and a lot of
people are wearing sunglasses, you know,
well, the fraction of pixels that
change, right? Even when people are
wearing sunglasses doesn't change that
much. Um, maybe if it's Halloween and
people are wearing crazy large costumes,
maybe that would change. But this is
actually a very robust algorithm because
it's so simple. In contrast, if you
trained on data with no one wearing
sunglasses, uh, because, you know, it's
not sun's not that hot these days,
right? Then with everyone starts to wear
sunglasses, this is actually less
robust. So one of the advantages of very
simple non-achine learning based systems
is they may be less susceptible to data
drift because maybe I tune this
parameter epsilon you know to a limited
data set but even when the data changes
this tuning quite robust but if I train
a neuronet network with say thousands or
tens of thousands of parameters then I'm
more likely to have overfitit to people
without sunglasses. So when people start
wearing sunglasses, um you're more
likely to have to update this model,
right? And um if you are building a
um
sorry
if you're building a them.
Um, it turns out to be incredibly
helpful if you can get user permission
to stream a little bit of data back to
your cloud hosted service so that
respecting user privacy being careful
often transpar privacy practices I think
that privacy is really important right
so do be transparent do the right thing
for users um and if you're able to do
that and get a little bit of data back
to your cloud to plot dashboards
And maybe one one practice I've seen is
um when building a high stakes
application uh one good practice would
be to gather your team together and um
get a diverse set of opinions on all the
things that could change and all the
things that could go wrong. And um I've
built quite a few machine learning
systems and I found that when we sit
down and brainstorm all the things that
could go wrong including the data
distribution changes, I don't think I
have ever seen something go wrong in
real life that we did not identify as a
possible problem. I might be wrong, but
at least right now when we sat down, we
really brainstorm all things that go
wrong. I think I have yet to see
something go wrong that was not on the
list of stuff that we brainstormed.
Right? And so if you brainstorm and and
and this is true for safety critical
applications as well, right? It turns
out creative teams, you can actually
think of all sorts of things that could
change in the data or things could go
wrong. And that then lets you um try to
design a set of dashboards or metrics to
put in place to monitor whether or not
any of the things that you think might
go wrong actually do go wrong. So um we
may put in place dashboards like um how
how often it turns out reauthentication
is a is a common thing. How often does a
user need to authenticate twice before
they let through? That's a that's
actually a sign of user frustration,
right? So it's build a dashboard to do
that. How often does a user have to try
twice? It probably means something went
wrong the first time. Um how often do
you accept versus reject the user? Um
and how what is the latency of the
system? And I find that just as it's
difficult to know in advance what's in
your data, it's actually difficult to
know in advance what dashboard will be
the most useful. And so the best
practice I tend to recommend is
brainstorm a lot of things to go wrong.
Brainstorm a lot of metrics. Um and then
just you know create very rich
dashboards where this is time latency
time uh reauthentication
right um
time the the number of zeros versus ones
and then draw plots
over time
to see how these rates trend over time.
And if you're able to have a lot of
dashboards and sample and just, you
know, look at some of the data for where
you suspect you may be making a mistake,
that often is then a good way for you to
have a higher chance of spotting um when
there might be a problem. And in the
times I've built large dashboards with,
you know, 20 30 metrics, I found that
it's surprisingly difficult to know in
advance which dashboards would turn out
to be useful. Um I think in in
exploratory data analysis in data
science again because we often don't
know what's in the data or what the data
will give us in the future. We just you
know frankly plot a lot of stuff and
then go and figure out from there what
is interesting right? So the cost of
plotting something um in a Jupyter
notebook is fairly low. So let's just
plot a lot of stuff have a lot of
dashboards and if you end up with you
know 30 50 100 dashboards tracking these
metrics over time then hopefully in a
few days or a few weeks you figure out
that a lot of them are really boring. So
we figure out that well latency is just
not a thing because with cloud hosted
deployment it's just very constant. So
well let's get rid of that because
that's just a very boring plot. I'm just
not worried about that. And so we often
plot a lot of things and then prune back
to then have a smaller number of metrics
that we track and monitor um for the
long term. And then eventually when you
get a sense of um
you know this being the normal range for
some metric, you can then also put in
place upper and lower alarms. um so that
if it ever goes above or below certain
bounds, they'll trigger an alarm like go
page someone to take a look to figure
out something's gone wrong. That make
sense? And so unfortunately the the um
just because you train a model a lot of
the time in a real world production
setting it doesn't mean you're done
because you deploy it and then the world
will give you surprising data and having
a plan to monitor what happens as well
as to maintain the model meaning get get
new data update the system um to fix
problems as they arise. That is often an
important part of um the practicalities
of uh deploying machine learning system
as well.